Guide to the Pierre Bédard Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Pierre Bédard Papers
1919-1970.
Bédard, Pierre, 1895-1970.
2.5 linear ft (2400 items in 6 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0095
4078419
This collection contains the papers of Pierre Bédard including correspondence, photographs, and printed matter.
Biographical Note
Pierre Bédard received his B.A. from Harvard College in 1917; became assistant secretary to the American Delegation at the Versailles Peace Conference in 1919; was analyst to France for Columbia Broadcasting System, 1937-1940; counselor to the French Military Mission to the U.S., 1943-44; Director of the French Institute, 1929-1952; and President of Parsons School of Design, 1952-1958.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, notes, photographs, memorabilia, clippings and printed matter. The correspondence series includes letters from Charles Boyer, William J. Donovan, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Paul Hazard, Cordell Hull, André Maurois, Edward R. Murrow and Thornton Wilder, mostly relating to Bédard's interest in Franco-American relations, as well as three letters from Calvin Coolidge to Bédard's father, J. Armand Bédard. In addition to transcripts of Bédard's broadcasts to France made over Columbia Broadcasting System between 1937 and 1940, the collection contains files from the French Military Mission to the United States during the second World War, the French Institute in the Unites States, and Parsons School of Design in New York City. The photographs series contains Bédard's photographs album from the first World War and photographs from the Versailles Peace Conference in 1919.
Arrangement
Selected items cataloged; remainder arranged. This collection is arranged in one series:
Series I: Pierre Bédard Papers, 1919-1970
Subjects
Columbia Broadcasting System, inc.; French Institute in the United States.; Parsons School of Design.; Hazard, Paul, 1878-1944.; World War, 1914-1918--Treaties.; Photoprints; Diplomats
Acquisition
06/12/86 M-86-06-12 Papers Bédard, Mrs. Pierre Gift
Gift of Mrs. Pierre Bédard, 1986.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 2-6. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Pierre Bédard Papers, 1919-1970
  - Cataloged Correspondence
    - Barzun, Jacques (Box 1)
    - Boyer, Charles (Box 1)
    - Coolidge, Calvin (Box 1)
    - Coty, Rene (Box 1)
    - Cousins, Norman (Box 1)
    - Donovan, William J. (Box 1)
    - Dulles, John Foster (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, Milton S. (Box 1)
    - Flanner, Janet (Box 1)
    - Hazard, Paul (Box 1)
    - Kent, Rockwell (Box 1)
    - Juin, Alphonse-Pierre (Box 1)
    - Hull, Cordell (Box 1)
    - Lodge, Henry Cabot (Box 1)
    - MeCloy, John (Box 1)
    - Maurois, Andre (Box 1)
    - Moe, Henry Allen (Box 1)
    - Murrow, Edward R. (Box 1)
    - Paley, William S. (Box 1)
    - Parsons, Geoffrey (Box 1)
    - Wilder, Thornton (Box 1)
  - Cataloged Photographs
    - Juin, Alphonse-Pierre (Box 6)
    - Swanson, Gloria (Box 1)
  - Arranged Correspondence
    - A - W (Box 1)
    - Adam, George (Box 1)
    - Alphand, Hervé (Box 1)
    - Arnauld de la Pierre, Lothar von (Box 1)
    - Bédard, Pierre (carbons) (Box 1)
    - Bethouart, M.E. (Box 1)
    - Bonnet, Henri (Box 1)
    - Bosworth, Welles (Box 1)
    - Dillon, Douglas (Box 1)
    - Focillon, Henri (Box 1)
    - Forbes, Malcolm (Box 1)
    - Heckscher, August (Box 1)
    - Leahy, William (Box 1)
    - Lucet, Charles (Box 1)
    - Morize, Andre (Box 1)
    - Napoleon [Prince] (Box 1)
    - Pell, Claiborne (Box 1)
    - Weygand, [General] (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts
    - "Art and Industry" (1931) (Box 1)
    - [Bartholdi Exhibition]: (1936) (Box 1)
    - Columbia Broadcasting, Broadcasts to France
      - 1937-1940, Introduction (Box 1)
      - 1937 (Box 1)
      - 1938 (Box 1)
      - 1939 (Box 2)
      - 1940 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Items (Box 2)
      - Translations, 1937-1940 (Box 2)
      - Jacques Kayser Interview (Box 2)
        - Translations
          - Chamberlain, Neville (Box 2)
          - Hitler, Adolf (Box 2)
          - Hull, Cordell (Box 2)
          - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 2)
    - "Design and Mass Culture" (1950) (Box 2)
    - "Discussion of Rousseau's Project for a League to Enforce Peace" (Box 2)
    - "Does an Industrial Society Need the Arts" (1965) (Box 2)
    - "Education of a Designer" (1958) (Box 2)
    - "Fireplug No. 1" (1949) (Box 2)
    - "France and the French Today" (1942) (Box 2)
    - Middlebury College Commencement Address (1954) (Box 2)
    - Ripon College Commencement Address (1949) (Box 2)
  - Subject Files
    - American Friends of Versailles (Box 3)
    - Bédard, Gertrude. Biographical Information (Box 3)
    - Bédard, Pierre. Biographical Information
      - Documents (Box 3)
      - Documents, Military (WWI) (Box 3)
      - World War I (Box 3)
    - Bédard, Pierre and Gertrude
      - Luncheons and Dinners (Box 3)
        - Guest Lists (Box 3)
    - The Century Association
      - American Garlic Society (Box 3)
      - Coffee House Club (Box 3)
    - Columbia Broadcasting
      - Press Releases (Box 3)
    - DeGaulle, Charles (Box 3)
    - Federation de l'Alliance Francaise (Box 3)
    - Federation of French Alliances (Box 3)
    - France-America Society (Box 3)
    - France-America Society, Bethouart Luncheon (1969) (Box 3)
    - The French Institute (Box 3)
    - The French Institute, Museum of French Art. Project Notes, Reports (Box 3)
    - French Military Mission (WWII)
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - Bédard, Pierre. Notebook & identification (Box 3)
      - Bethouart, M.E. Biographical information (Box 3)
      - Speeches (Box 3)
      - Giraud, Henri (Box 3)
      - Membership Lists (Box 3)
      - Press Releases (Box 3)
    - Harvard Round Table, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Institute of International Education (Box 3)
    - Instituto de Puerto Rico (Box 3)
    - International Institute of American Civilization
      - Correspondence (Box 3)
      - By-laws, etc (Box 3)
    - Lafayette Bicentennial (Box 3)
    - National Student Federation of the U.S.A. (Box 3)
    - The Parsons School (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - Audits & Budgets (Box 4)
      - Bédard, Pierre
        - Speeches (Box 4)
        - Travel (Box 4)
      - Finances (Box 4)
      - Heckscher, August. Speech (Box 4)
      - Reports to Trustees (Box 4)
    - Science for Humanity Congress (Box 4)
    - University Club of Paris (Box 4)
  - Photographs
    - Alphand, Hervé (Box 4)
    - Benda, Julien (Box 4)
    - Bédard, Pierre (WWl) (Box 4)
    - Bédard, Pierre and Gertrude Bédard (Box 4)
    - Bethouart, M.E. (in Box 6) (Box 6)
    - The Century Association, American Garlic Society (Box 4)
    - Century Club Centennial (Coffee House Club) (Box 4)
    - City Investing (Box 4)
    - Columbia Broadcasting (Box 4)
    - Federation of French Alliances (Box 4)
    - The French Institute (Box 4)
    - Giraud, Henri (Box 4)
    - Howard, Cecil - sculpture (Box 4)
    - Lafayette Bicentennial (Box 4)
    - Middlebury College Commencement (Box 4)
    - The Parsons School (Box 4)
    - Pompidou, George (Box 4)
    - Ripon College Commencement (Box 4)
    - World War I. Bédard Photograph Album (l) - (2)
      - Paris (Box 4)
      - Versailles (Box 4)
      - Versailles Peace Conference (Box 4)
      - Versailles Peace Conference, Military Staffs (Box 4)
  - Memorabilia
    - Invitations
      - Presidential (Box 5)
    - New York Society of Military and Naval Officers (Box 5)
    - The Parsons School (Box 5)
    - Programs and Menus (Box 5)
      - Les amis déscoffier (Box 5)
      - France-America Society (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - World War I (Box 5)
  - Clippings
    - Columbia Broadcasting (Box 5)
    - Federation of French Alliances (Box 5)
    - The French Institute (Box 5)
      - Museum of French Art (Box 5)
    - French Military Mission (WWII) (Box 5)
    - The Parsons School (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (l) - (2) (Box 5)
  - Printed Matter
    - American Society for International Law (Box 5)
    - The Century Association (Box 5)
    - France-America Society (Box 5)
    - The French Institute
      - General (Box 5)
      - Bulletins (in Box 6) (Box 6)
      - Museum of French Art (Box 5)
        - Catalogues (l) - (2) (Box 5)
        - Programmes (in Box 6) (Box 6)
    - International Institute of American Civilization (Box 5)
    - Lafayette Bicentennial (Box 5)
    - The Parsons School (Box 5)
    - Professional Children's School (Box 5)
  - Books
    - Marie [Queen of Roumania]. Ode to Roumania. (Paris, 1923) (Box 6)
    - Price, G. Ward. Giraud and the African Scene. (New York, 1944) (Box 6)
  - Oversize Materials
    - Cataloged Photograph: Juin, Alphonse-Pierre (Box 6)
    - Photograph: Bethouart, M.E. (Box 6)
      - Printed Matter
        - The French Institute, Bulletins (Box 6)
          - Museum of French Art, Programmes (Box 6)